Brandon Essler

Full-stack Software Engineer with over a decade of experience in Telecom, Healthcare, FinTech, and Ecommerce seeking new challenges. Ideally pursuing roles that involve Machine Learning, Software Architecture, or DevOps responsibilities that align with recent masters-level coursework in Deep Learning and Computer Vision.

Orlando, FL 32801

(402) 639-8835

brandon@essler.me

EXPERIENCE

OMNEverse Software Solutions — Freelance Software Developer

JUL 2022 - PRESENT

- Builds, deploys, and delivers full-stack, custom applications using diverse tech stacks including Xamarin Forms, React Native, and Microsoft Azure.
- Sources and vets quality clients from a variety of outlets, achieving successful contract negotiation and onboarding.
- Leads business discussions to discover client needs, offer specific technical solutions, and execute project plans on schedule.
- Extracts detailed requirements from clients, controlling project scope, and staying within budget while still delivering clients' visions.
- Manages software and service licensing and billing for the business and for clients prior to delivery.

Mutual of Omaha — Senior Software Engineer

NOV 2019 - JUL 2022 (2y 8m)

- Administered AWS platform to enable efficient day-to-day development operations for the entire division – using services such as Lambda, EC2, CloudWatch, S3/Glacier, ECS, DynamoDB, RDS, CloudFormation, Cognito/IAM.
- Developed AWS Lambdas using Python and Amazon Connect contact flows.
- Modernized technology across software applications, including Gradle package updates, refactoring legacy codebases, and Jenkins pipeline migrations.
- Actively collaborated with vendors to improve product functionality and enhance documentation.
- Built new features for group insurance billing applications leveraging Java, Groovy, Spock, Oracle DB (PL/SQL), Gradle, Kafka, Bitbucket, Docker, and Jenkins with Blue Ocean.
- Created complex internal tools, like an event-driven test harness for system testing among multiple teams in a distributed environment with a Kafka pub/sub architecture.
- Implemented front-end feature requests for React applications based on user and stakeholder feedback.
- Improved member data transfer process by migrating batch jobs from using standard Linux SFTP commands to MOVEit, an enterprise-level secure managed file transfer platform, for efficient retrieval and delivery of data to third parties.

Intrado — *Software Engineer*

NOV 2013 - NOV 2019 (6y)

- Supported several high-profile, high-revenue clients, including Walmart and CVS, as primary subject matter expert, spanning dozens of applications.
- Lead the effort to create unit testing standards for the organization's Java code base, using JUnit and Mockito.
- Maintained a popular internal tool used to generate the skeleton of new VXML

TECHNOLOGIES

Java / Groovy	••••
Python	••••
AWS / Azure	••••
JavaScript	••••
SQL / PL/SQL	••••
Spring Boot	•••00
React	•••00
Gradle / Maven	•••00
Jenkins	•••00
SOAP/REST APIs	•••00
C#	•••00
Docker	•••00
iOS / Android	••000
Kafka	••000
PowerShell	••000
Perl	••000

MORE ABOUT ME

My biggest achievement is...

Being singled out to work on-site with a client development team for the largest retailer in the world at their own HQ to improve communication and response time between teams.

Right now I'm learning...

3D modeling with Blender to create my own custom 3D printing designs.

I want to work for a company that...

Treats people like people. Where we're all humans first and coworkers second.

Interests

Kayaking, mindfulness, entrepreneurship.

- applications.
- Worked face-to-face and onsite with client developer teams to collaborate and overcome difficulties integrating systems.
- Participated in the annual company hackathon, the latest of which involved the creation of a Progressive Web App and the use of CI/CD tools including PCF, Artifactory, and Concourse.
- Successfully filed a patent for a custom notifications application, which was approved.
- Utilized JavaScript to develop complex back-end business logic, integrated with VXML front-end to enhance user experience.
- Managed batch process and SFTP servers for client access to daily reports and other file-based deliverables.

Run Networks — iOS Application Developer

JAN 2011 - JAN 2013 (2y)

- Developed C# apps and web services that executed MS SQL queries and API calls.
- Created web programs with Perl and PHP, including one which parsed data from existing websites and inserted into a SQL database.
- Wrote Powershell scripts to automate tasks, such as verifying bit-level backups and migrating a Worldox document structure.
- Set up a Git environment for version control and development staging to be used by the entire organization.

Gallup — Computer Science Intern

APR 2009 - SEP 2009 (6m)

- Mastered multiple Adobe products including Photoshop, Illustrator, and Flash/ActionScript.
- Created several freelance projects for clients, blending skills in art, design, and programming.

EDUCATION

University of Nebraska, Omaha — *Graduate Certificate in Al*

JAN 2021 - DEC 2022

- Performed novel data augmentation on existing skeleton-based datasets for egocentric Virtual Reality (VR) applications – using OpenCV and YOLOv7.
- Presented a project on Collision Avoidance for NVIDIA Jetson Nano processor and JetBot chassis – using Python, PyTorch, TensorRT, and CUDA Toolkit.
- Wrote a Deep Learning research paper on the topic of Independent Comparison of Prominent Generative Models – using TensorFlow, Keras, and Matplotlib's Pyplot.

University of Nebraska, Omaha — B.Sc. in Computer Science

JAN 2008 - MAY 2012

- Created a video game on the Game Boy Advance system as part of a group, using C and utilizing the system's limited memory.
- Developed a video game for use on Windows Live as part of a group, using C# and Microsoft's XNA framework.
- Competed in the ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, solving math-based programming problems using Java.
- Delivered a lightning talk on a project involving a Perl CGI script and HTML forms.
- Implemented numerical method algorithms in C to approximate functions, derivatives, and antiderivatives.

SNIPPETS

3D Printing

3D printed a 3D printer. Both will be used to print a 3rd 3D printer, and next a CNC router.

FPV Drone Flying

Sourced and hand built a first person view (FPV) racing drone with a 115 MPH top speed.

Motorcycle Modding

Continually modifies a Kawasaki Z650 motorcycle. Recently swapped out long-stem mirrors for cleaner, more streamlined bar-end mirrors.